<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-roll-mpl-parameter-configuration-01">
  <?rfc toc="yes"?>         <!-- generate a table of contents -->
  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>     <!-- use anchors instead of numbers for references -->
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>   <!-- alphabetize the references -->
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>    <!-- conserve vertical whitespace -->
  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>  <!-- but keep a blank line between list items -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPL Conf. for DHCPv6">MPL Parameter Configuration Option for DHCPv6</title>

    <author initials="Y." surname="Doi"
	    fullname="Yusuke Doi">
      <organization>TOSHIBA Corporation</organization>

      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>Komukai Toshiba Cho 1</street>
	  <street>Saiwai-Ku</street>
	  <city>Kawasaki</city> <region>Kanagawa</region>
	  <code>2128582</code>
	  <country>JAPAN</country>
	</postal>

	<phone>+81-45-342-7230</phone>
	<email>yusuke.doi@toshiba.co.jp</email>
	<uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="M." surname="Gillmore"
	    fullname="Matthew Gillmore">
      <organization>Itron, Inc</organization>

      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>2111 N Molter Rd.</street>
	  <city>Liberty Lake</city> <region>WA</region>
	  <code>99019</code>
	  <country>USA</country>
	</postal>

	<email>matthew.gillmore@itron.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="July" year="2014"/>

    <area>rtg</area>
    <workgroup>roll</workgroup>
    <keyword>MPL, DHCPv6</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
This draft defines a way to configure MPL parameter set via DHCPv6 option. MPL has a set of parameters to control its behavior, and the parameter set is often configured as a network-wide parameter because the parameter set should be identical for each MPL forwarder in an MPL domain. Using the MPL Parameter Configuration Option defined in this document, a network can be configured with a single set of MPL parameter easily.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
  
<section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
  
  <t>
    Multicast Protocol for Low power and Lossy Networks
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-roll-trickle-mcast">(MPL)</xref> defines a
    protocol to make a multicast network among low power and lossy
    network i.e. wireless mesh networks. MPL has a set of parameters to
    control its behavior and tradeoff between end-to-end delay and
    network utilization. In most environments, the default parameters
    are acceptable. However, in some environments, the parameter set
    must be configured carefully in order to meet the requirements of
    each environment. According to the MPL draft section 5.4, each
    parameter in the set should be same for all nodes within an MPL
    domain. And the MPL draft does not define a method to configure the
    MPL parameter set.
  </t>
  <t>
    Some managed wireless mesh networks may have a DHCP server to
    configure network parameters. MPL parameter set shall be considered
    as a part of network parameters (nodes in an MPL domain should use
    an identical parameter set). This document is to define the way to
    distribute parameter sets for MPL forwarders as a simple
    <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6</xref> option.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="MPL Parameter Configuration Option" anchor="mpl-parameter-configuration-option">
  
  <t>
    Per MPL domain, there are following 10 parameters. An MPL domain is
    defined by an MPL domain address.
  </t>
  <t><list style="symbols">
    <t>
      
        PROACTIVE_FORWARDING
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        SEED_SET_ENTRY_LIFETIME
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        DATA_MESSAGE_IMIN
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        DATA_MESSAGE_IMAX
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        DATA_MESSAGE_K
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        DATA_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMIN
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMAX
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        CONTROL_MESSAGE_K
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        CONTROL_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS
      
    </t>
  </list></t>
  <t>
    One network may have multiple MPL domains with different
    configurations. To configure more than one MPL domain via DHCP,
    there may be more than one MPL Parameter Configuration Option given
    to DHCP clients from a DHCP server.
  </t>
  <section title="Unsigned Short Floating Point" anchor="unsigned-short-floating-point">
    
    <t>
      MPL has many timer parameters. Expected range of the timers
      depends on the network topology or MAC/PHY nature. To accommodate
      wide range of timer values efficiently, the MPL Parameter
      Configuration Option uses base-10 unsigned short floating point
      number with 3-bit exponent and 13-bit significand defined as
      follows (exp. stands for exponent).
    </t>
    <figure><artwork>
 0                   1           
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| exp.|      significand        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork></figure>
    <t>
      The represented value is (significand) * 10^(exp.). The minimum
      exponent is 0 (binary 000) and the maximum is 6 (binary 110).
      exp=7 (binary 111) is reserved for future use. The minimum
      significand is 0 (all 0) and the maximum is 8191 (all 1).
    </t>
    <t>
      Unlike IEEE754 half precision floating point (binary16), there is
      no sign bit (no negative value for a timer), exponent is not
      biased (no fractional value for a timer), no implicit leading 1 in
      siginificand, and base is 10. Therefore, there could be more than
      one representation for a value.
    </t>
    <t>
      Followings are examples of common timer values represented by unit
      of millisecond.
    </t>
    <t><list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="One second (1,000 milliseconds):">
          
            exp = 3, significand = 1, 0x6001.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="One minute (60,000 milliseconds):">
          
            exp = 4, significand = 6, 0x8006.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="One hour (3,600,000 milliseconds):">
          
            exp = 5, significand = 36, 0xa024.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="One day (86,400,000 milliseconds):">
          
            exp = 5, significand = 864, 0xa360
          
        </t>
    </list></t>
    <t>
      Maximum timer length represented by an unsigned short floating
      point with millisecond precision is 8191 * 10^6 milliseconds (13
      weeks 3 days 19 hours 16 minutes 40 seconds).
    </t>
    <t>
      With exponent and significand, an unsigned short floating point
      (usfp) can be encoded as follows.
    </t>
    <figure><artwork>
usfp = (exponent &lt;&lt; 13)|(0x1fff &amp; significand);
</artwork></figure>
  </section>
  <section title="MPL Parameter Configuration Option Format" anchor="mpl-parameter-configuration-option-format">
    
    <t>
      To distribute a configuration of an MPL domain or a default value
      for all MPL domains (wildcard) under the network managed by the
      DHCP server, this document defines a DHCPv6 option format as
      follows. Short floating point format is used to describe wide
      range of timer values.
    </t>
    <figure><artwork>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    OPTION_MPL_PARAMETERS      |          option_len           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|P| Z |   C_K   | Z2  |  DM_K   |         SE_LIFETIME           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         DM_IMIN               |          DM_IMAX              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         DM_T_EXP              |          C_IMIN               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         C_IMAX                |          C_T_EXP              |     
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

(if option_len = 32 )
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          MPL Domain Address  (128bits)                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          (cont'ed)                                            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          (cont'ed)                                            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          (cont'ed)                                            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork></figure>
    <t><list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="OPTION_MPL_PARAMETERS:">
          
            DHCPv6 option identifier (not yet assigned).
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="option_len:">
          
            Length of the option. It SHOULD be 16 (without MPL domain
            address) or 32 (with MPL domain address)
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="P (1 bit):">
          
            A flag to indicate PROACTIVE_FORWARDING
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="Z (1 bit)">
          
            Reserved. Should be 0.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="C_K (5 bits):">
          
            CONTROL_MESSAGE_K.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="Z2 (3 bits)">
          
            Reserved. Should be all 0.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="DM_K (5 bits):">
          
            DATA_MESSAGE_K.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="SE_LIFETIME:">
          
            SEED_SET_ENTRY_LIFETIME. The unit is millisecond and the
            type is unsigned short floating point.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="DM_IMIN:">
          
            DATA_MESSAGE_IMIN. The unit is millisecond and the type is
            unsigned short floating point.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="DM_IMAX:">
          
            DATA_MESSAGE_IMAX. The unit is millisecond and the type is
            unsigned short floating point.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="DM_T_EXP:">
          
            DATA_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS. The unit is millisecond and
            the type is unsigned short floating point.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="C_IMIN:">
          
            CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMIN. The unit is millisecond and the type
            is unsigned short floating point.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="C_IMAX:">
          
            CONTROL_MESSAGE_IMAX. The unit is millisecond and the type
            is unsigned short floating point.
          
        </t>
      <t hangText="C_T_EXP:">
          
            CONTROL_MESSAGE_TIMER_EXPIRATIONS. The unit is millisecond
            and the type is unsigned short floating point.
          
        </t>
    </list></t>
  </section>
  <section title="DHCPv6 Client Behavior" anchor="dhcpv6-client-behavior">
    
    <t>
      Clients MAY request MPL Parameter Configuration Option, as
      described in <xref target="RFC3315">RFC3315</xref>, sections
      17.1.1, 18.1.1, 18.1.3, 18.1.4, 18.1.5 and 22.7. As a convenience
      to the reader, we mention here that the client includes requested
      option codes in Option Request Option.
    </t>
    <t>
      Clients MUST discard MPL Parameter Configuration Option if it is
      invalid (i.e. it sets reserved bits or it has timers with reserved
      exp=7 in Unsigned Short Floating Point).
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="MPL Forwarder Behavior" anchor="mpl-forwarder-behavior">
    
    <t>
      If a DHCPv6 client requests and receives MPL Parameter
      Configuration Option, the node MAY join the MPL domain given by
      the option and act as an MPL forwarder. Each joining node SHOULD
      configure its MPL forwarder with the given parameter set for the
      MPL domain.
    </t>
    <t>
      The priority of MPL Parameter Configuration applied for an MPL
      Domain is as follows (high to low).
    </t>
    <t><list style="symbols">
      <t>
        
          Specific MPL Parameter Configuration to the MPL Domain
          (optlen=32)
        
      </t>
      <t>
        
          Wildcard MPL Parameter Configuration (optlen=16)
        
      </t>
      <t>
        
          Default configuration given in the MPL specification.
        
      </t>
    </list></t>
    <t>
      There SHALL be no more than one MPL Parameter Configuration Option
      for a MPL domain or the wildcard. Thus, the order of DHCPv6
      options in the packet has no effect on precedence.
    </t>
    <t>
      A node MAY leave from an MPL domain if the following two
      conditions are satisfied. 1) The MPL domain is configured by a
      DHCPv6 option from a DHCPv6 server previously. 2) The node has
      received an updated MPL Parameter Configuration Option without a
      configuration for the MPL domain.
    </t>
    <t>
      MPL parameter may be updated occasionally. With stateful DHCPv6,
      updates can be done when the renewal timer expires.
      <xref target="RFC4242">Information Refresh Time Option</xref>
      shall be used to keep each forwarders updated.
    </t>
    <t>
      To reduce periodical update traffic a node may try to use very
      long interval between updates. In the case, reconfigure shall be
      used to keep forwarder parameter sets synchronized. For stateless
      DHCPv6,
      <xref target="I-D.jiang-dhc-stateless-reconfiguration"/>
      may be used (if approved).
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="DHCPv6 Server Behavior" anchor="dhcpv6-server-behavior">
    
    <t>
      Sections 17.2.2 and 18.2 of <xref target="RFC3315">RFC3315</xref>
      govern server operation in regards to option assignment. As a
      convenience to the reader, we mention here that the server will
      send MPL Parameter Configuration Option only if configured with
      specific value for MPL Parameter Configuration Option and the
      client requested it.
    </t>
    <t>
      Servers SHALL ignore incoming MPL Parameter Configuration Option.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="DHCPv6 Relay Behavior" anchor="dhcpv6-relay-behavior">
    
    <t>
      It's never appropriate for a relay agent to add options to a
      message heading toward the client, and relay agents don't actually
      construct Relay-Reply messages anyway. There are no additional
      requirements for relays.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Operational Considerations" anchor="operational-considerations">
    
    <t>
      A parameter set for an MPL domain SHOULD NOT updated more often
      than two times of expected refresh interval.
    </t>
    <t>
      If a node with MPL forwarder configured by MPL Parameter
      configuration Option failed to refresh the option for two times of
      information refresh time, it SHALL suspend the MPL forwarders of
      MPL domains configured by the option. MPL forwarders configured by
      other methods such as static configuration file SHALL NOT be
      suspended.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations">
  
  <t>
    A DHCPv6 option code for MPL Parameter Configuration Option needs to
    be assigned from IANA.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">
  
  <t>
    A forged option may cause excessive layer-2 broadcasting.
    Implementations should set reasonable bounds for each parameter. For
    example, not too high K, not too low IMIN, etc. These may be
    implementation dependent or may be derived from MAC/PHY
    specifications. DHCP server or the network itself shall be trusted
    by some means including network access control or DHCP
    authentications.
  </t>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="../refs/reference.RFC.3315.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="../refs/reference.RFC.4242.xml"?>
      <!-- ?rfc include="refs/reference.RFC.6282.xml"? -->
      <?rfc include="../refs/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-roll-trickle-mcast-07.xml"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Non-Normative References">
      <?rfc include="../refs/reference.I-D.draft-jiang-dhc-stateless-reconfiguration-01.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="../refs/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines.xml"?>
    </references>
<section title="Update History" anchor="update-history">
  
  <t>
    Updates on draft-doi-roll-mpl-configuration-05 to
    draft-ietf-roll-mpl-configuration-01:
  </t>
  <t><list style="symbols">
    <t>
      
        Operational considerations (normative) and appendix
        considerations (non-normative) are added (Issue #157)
      
    </t>
    <t>
      
        More control on nodes / allow constrained nodes to ignore the
        configuration: "the node s/SHOULD/MAY/ join the MPL domain
        given by the option" (Issue #158)
      
    </t>
  </list></t>
  <t>
    Updates on draft-doi-roll-mpl-configuration-05 to
    draft-ietf-roll-mpl-configuration-00:
  </t>
  <t><list style="symbols">
    <t>
      
        I-D renamed.
      
    </t>
  </list></t>
</section>
<section title="Considerations on Inconsistent Parameter Set" anchor="considerations-on-inconsistent-parameter-set">
  
  <t>
    This draft introduces dynamic update of MPL parameters. Because the
    update process is not synchronized, nodes may have inconsistent
    parameter set.
  </t>
  <t>
    Inconsistent parameter may reduce performance. On the other hand, it
    shall work as long as both parameter set are reasonable parameter
    set for a given communication load. As motivations for parameter
    update are update on environment, node density, or communication
    load, operators of MPL networks shall be aware of unupdated nodes
    and make sure old and new parameter sets are reasonable for expected
    refresh intervals.
  </t>
</section>


  </back>
</rfc>
